Guide to Montana Historical Society Board of Trustees records 1865-2006
Montana Historical Society
Montana Historical Society Board of Trustees records,
1865-2006
Montana Historical Society Archives
MHS 1
Montana Historical Society. Board of Trustees.
7 linear feet of shelf space
The Montana Historical Society Board of Trustees is the governing board of the Society. Records includes correspondence with Society directors, files of individual board members, minutes, organizational records, reports, and miscellany.
On December 21, 1864 Francis M. Thompson introduced into the Territorial legislature, Council Bill 15 to incorporate the Historical Society of Montana, as a private organization. The purpose of the Society was “…to collect and arrange facts in regard to the early history of this Territory…." The bill was signed into law on February 2, 1865. The Society held its first organizational meeting later that month. Among the incorporators were Granville Stuart, H. L. Hosmer, C. P. Higgins, John Owens, and W. F. Sanders. The Society membership was limited to a few prominent Montana pioneers, who had to be elected by unanimous election by the members.
The Society began collecting reminiscences and other memorabilia of the early pioneers. Tragically, these collections burned in the disastrous 1874 fire in downtown Helena. Immediately after the fire, the Society contacted many of the original pioneers and obtained replacement reminiscences, diaries, and letters. They also began the intensive collection of the territory’s newspapers, publications of government expeditions, artifacts, and other items of interest. The collections were housed in the Lewis and Clark County Courthouse from 1886 until the completion of the new Capitol building in 1902.
The early history of the Society was one of a gradual increase in government involvement. In 1873 the legislature appropriated $150 to buy additional manuscripts and books. By 1887 the Territory was paying rent for housing the library and the salary of the librarian. In 1891 the collections were officially transferred to State control. And two years later the Governor was given the authority to appoint the Board of Trustees. In 1895 the legislature changed the name to “The Historical and Miscellaneous Library”. This name was retained until the 1923 legislature restored the original name. Finally in 1963 the name was changed to its present Montana Historical Society.
A separate building for the Society was planned as early as the mid 1920s, but the Depression, World War II, and other factors delayed the building until 1953 when the Veterans and Pioneers Building was completed. In 1951 K. Ross Toole was hired as the first professional director. His major task was to plan for the new building, and the varied programs which it would enable. Among these programs were a formal museum, art galleries, the library, and a magazine.
The original Historical Society of Montana was governed by a five member Board of Trustees consisting of the President, the Recording Secretary, the Corresponding Secretary, the Treasurer, and the Librarian. Beginning 1891, when the state legislature established the Historical Society of Montana as a state agency, the Board of Trustees was appointed by the Governor. In 1949 the Board was expanded to 15 members. From the Board of Trustees, an Executive Board is chosen consisting of the President, Vice President, and three additional Board members.
During most of its existence, the Board has played a secondary role, leaving the active management of the Society to the paid staff. The functions of the Board consist of overall policy decisions, approval of all deeds, leases, and other legal documents executed by the Society, and other duties as set forth in current legislation.
Records consist of miscellaneous correspondence (1874-1890, 1947); correspondence (1951-2006) with the Directors; files for individual Board members; minutes of the Board (1865-2003); organizational materials, including bylaws and the enabling act, lists of Board members, etc.; reports (1875-1920, 1934, 1955); and a subject file. There is a subgroup for records kept by long-time Board member Merrill Burlingame concerning the Society and his service on the Board.
The collection is arranged by subgroups and series.
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Historical societies, etc.-- Montana.; Museums--Montana.
Montana--History.
Montana.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Board of Trustees
  - Interoffice Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous, 1874-1890 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
    - Norman Winestine and J. B. Speer (re general membership, and preservation of records), 1947 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
    - Directors: K. Ross Toole, 1951-1958 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
    - Directors: Michael S. Kennedy, 1959-1966 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
    - Directors: Robert F. Morgan (interim director), 1966-1967 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
    - Directors: Sam Gilluly, 1967-1974 (Box-folder 1 / 6-8)
    - Directors: Ken Korte, 1974-1979 (Box-folder 1 / 9)
    - Directors: Robert Archibald, 1979-1988 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
    - Directors: Robert M. Clark (interim director), 1989 (Box-folder 1 / 11)
    - Directors: Lawrence Sommer, 1989-1992 (Box-folder 1 / 12)
    - Directors: Brian Cockhill, 1992-1998 (Box-folder 1 / 13-15)
    - Directors: Sharon McCabe (interim director), 1999 (Box-folder 1 / 16)
    - Directors: Arnold Olsen, 1999-2005 (Box-folder 1 / 17-20)
    - Directors: Mark Baumler (interim director), 2005-2006 (Box-folder 1 / 21)
    - Directors: (RESERVED), 2006 (Box-folder 1 / 22-25)
    - Board appointments, 1951-2005 (Box-folder 1 / 26)
    - Trustees: A (includes Virginia Anderson), 1964-1970 (Box-folder 1 / 27)
    - Trustees: Casey E. Barthelmess, 1958-1973 (Box-folder 1 / 28-29)
    - Trustees: B (includes Manson Bailey, James Beery, Jean Birch, Jean F. Bishop, Lena Bissonette, Ray O. Bjork, Charles Bovey, and John J. Burke; Merrill Burlingame files are in subgroup), 1951-2001 (Box-folder 1 / 30)
    - Trustees: Stuart Conner, 1987-1993 (Box-folder 1 / 31-33)
    - Trustees: C (includes Lew L. Callaway), 1951 (Box-folder 1 / 34)
    - Trustees: D (includes Tony Dalich, Joseph S. Dent, Jessie T. Duthie), 1952-1978 (Box-folder 1 / 35)
    - Trustees: E-F (includes Jeannie Eder, Charmaine R. Fisher, Tom Foor, Stella Foote, Timothy C. Fox), 1970-2003 (Box-folder 1 / 36)
    - Trustees: G (includes Sam Gilluly, Newell Gough), 1951-1979 (Box-folder 1 / 37)
    - Trustees: H (includes Warren P. Hall, Ben Harwood, Jack Hayne, Josephine Hepner, Anne Hibbard, William Holt, Helen Hornby, Joseph Kinsey Howard), 1951-2000 (Box-folder 1 / 38)
    - Trustees: J-K (includes O'Neil Jones, Howard Johnson, Marjorie King), 1955-1996 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
    - Trustees: L (includes Lester H. Loble, Virginia Lucht), 1957-1998 (Box-folder 2 / 2)
    - Trustees: E. E. "Boo" MacGilvra, 1954-1980 (Box-folder 2 / 3-6)
    - Trustees: William R. and Joyce Childs Mackay, 1954-1999 (Box-folder 2 / 7)
    - Trustees: M (includes Marie MacDonald, Vicki McCarthy, Susan McDaniel, Joe Medicine Crow), 1957-2000 (Box-folder 2 / 8)
    - Trustees: O-P (includes George W. O'Connor, Albert J. Partoll, Loren Perry, Harold Poulsen), 1954-1994 (Box-folder 2 / 9)
    - Trustees: R (includes Joseph E. Reber, James W. Reger, Richard Roeder, Mel Ruder, Henry S. Ruegamer), 1967-1994 (Box-folder 2 / 10)
    - Trustees: Harold G. "Hal" Stearns, 1954-1973, 1984-1991 (Box-folder 2 / 11)
    - Trustees: Branson G. Stevenson, 1956-1974, 1989 (Box-folder 2 / 12)
    - Trustees: S (includes Ruby Settle, Ward Shanahan, Whitney Smith, Willis B. Spear, Randall Swanberg), 1954-1994 (Box-folder 2 / 13)
    - Trustees: T-V (includes Dee C. Taylor, Ronald W. Torstenson, James Vanderbeck), 1970-1990 (Box-folder 2 / 14)
    - Trustees: W (includes Wilbur Werner, Portia B. White, Norman Winestine), 1951-1990 (Box-folder 2 / 15)
    - Trustees: (RESERVED), 1951-2006 (Box-folder 2 / 16-19)
  - Minutes
    - Minutes of meetings (scattered originals) (1873 meeting includes constitution), 1865-1894 (Box-folder 2 / 20)
    - Minutes of meetings (handwritten copies) (1885-1889 also includes annual reports to Governor), 1865-1894 (Box-folder 2 / 21)
    - Minutes of meetings, 1895-1954 (Box-folder 2 / 22-25)
    - Minutes of meetings (after 1967 minutes generally include financial reports and program reports), 1955-1981 (Box-folder 3 / 1-32)
    - Minutes of meetings (generally include financial reports and program reports), 1982-1998 (Box-folder 4 / 1-34)
    - Minutes of meetings (generally include financial reports and program reports; after 2000 include full packets), 1999-2003 (Box-folder 5 / 1-18)
    - Minutes of meetings (RESERVED) (include full packets), 2004 (Box-folder 5 / 19-)
    - Minutes of meetings (RESERVED) (include full packets), 2005 (Box-folder 6 / 1-)
  - Organizational Records
    - Bylaws, enabling act, 1865 (Box-folder 7 / 1)
    - Bylaws, 1966 (Box-folder 7 / 2)
    - Honorary membership (includes certificates, applications for membership, etc.), 1873-1891 (Box-folder 7 / 3)
    - List of board meetings, 1949-1969 (Box-folder 7 / 4)
    - Lists of board members and officers, 1865-2002 (Box-folder 7 / 5)
  - Reports
    - Annual and biennial reports to Governor, 1875-1889 (Box-folder 7 / 6)
    - Biennial reports to Governor (include librarian's report to board), 1911-1920, 1934 (Box-folder 7 / 7)
    - "A compendium of reports to the Board of Trustees...covering the principal activities of the past five years," by K. Ross Toole, 1956 (Box-folder 7 / 8)
    - Report to the Board by Wilbur Fisk Sanders, circa 1870 (Box-folder 7 / 9)
  - Subject Files
    - Director selection and evaluation, 1974, 1995-1999 (Box-folder 7 / 10)
    - Executive Committee, 1973-1997 (Box-folder 7 / 11)
    - Fundraising Committee, 1983-1985 (Box-folder 7 / 12)
    - Michael S. Kennedy controversy and firing (includes Merrill Burlingame's file, chronology, article copyright issue, copies of Board minutes re controversy, attorney A. L. Libra, report by Robert F. Morgan, Kennedy's lawsuit against Board, clippings), 1965-1966 (Box-folder 7 / 13-27)
    - Legislation: House Resolution in support of Society, 1874 (Box-folder 7 / 28)
    - Legislation: SB 52 (re continuation of Board; SB 40 (re state publication distribution); HB 559 (re Towe Ford Collection), 1983-1985 (Box-folder 7 / 29)
    - Long-Range Planning Committee, 1991-1994 (Box-folder 7 / 30)
    - Meeting planning, 2002-2003 (Box-folder 7 / 31-32)
    - Montana Historical Society Advisory Committee [proposed], 1989 (Box-folder 7 / 33)
    - Montana Statehood Centennial Bell Award, 1990-1998 (Box-folder 7 / 34)
    - Past trustees luncheon, 1995 (Box-folder 7 / 35)
    - Photo gallery of past Presidents (re placing of photos in conference room), 1989-1995 (Box-folder 7 / 36)
    - Trustees Award, 1978-2003 (Box-folder 7 / 37-41)
    - Trustees Educators Award, 1978-2003 (Box-folder 7 / 42-43)
    - Trustees retreat, 1985 (Box-folder 7 / 44)
- Trustee Merrill G. Burlingame
  - General Correspondence
    - K. Ross Toole, director, 1951-1957 (Box-folder 8 / 1)
    - Montana Historical Society chronological, 1951-1976 (Box-folder 8 / 2-13)
  - Subject Files
    - American Revolution Bicentennial, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 8 / 14)
    - Bylaws revision (includes Survey of bylaws and policy statements of other historical societies), 1949-1968 (Box-folder 8 / 15)
    - Historic Preservation Plan (draft), Montana Department of Fish and Game, 1970 (Box-folder 8 / 16)
    - Historic sites, Montana Highway Department, State Parks Division, 1957-1960 (Box-folder 8 / 17)
    - Historic sites, Montana Department of Fish and Game, 1968-1976 (Box-folder 8 / 18-21)
    - Historic sites, Montana Historical Society, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 8 / 22)
    - Historic sites: proposed nominations, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 8 / 23)
    - Montana State Historic Preservation Office, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 8 / 24-25)
    - Montana Territorial Centennial Commission, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 8 / 26)
    - Towe Ford Collection, 1967-1975 (Box-folder 8 / 27)
  - Miscellany
    - Certificate of appointment to Board, 1949 (Box-folder 8 / 28)
    - Donation by Caroline McGill, 1946 (Box-folder 8 / 29)
    - Montana history presentation by Brian Cockhill and Bob Gant, 1973 (Box-folder 8 / 30)